Everybody's craving, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said today, that craving... Understanding craving was seeing...
[SPEAKER_01]: I was seeing it as very unattractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: I started off with a super reflection and came down to what is unattractive in all things, as craving in regard to
[SPEAKER_01]: That is disgusting because of the things that it does.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that it implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that implies that you get caught up in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The self, the omniscience, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So cravings is unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that is how it should be, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the things, no matter what approach you take, it will end up leading to the same conclusions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like, oh, I don't have true cognizance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people have become skilled in sense-based, skilled in this, skilled in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All for the purpose of just revealing the same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not going to develop any new insights.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might develop new aspects of the same insights, depending on what approaches you take.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, you just to pursue whichever aspect you acquire, till the end, till the craving is gone, and you're another.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, it's kind of inseparable from what we spoke about the delight and the nature of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take delight for granted, you crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't even see the delight as phenomenon, the reason, what is delight?
[SPEAKER_00]: Delight, that joy that arises upon... that's all that it means craving is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the important thing is to not... well, not fall into a trap of thinking linearly, like, oh, first I felt, then I had the attitude of craving, then I'm delighting, then I must holding, then I get attached, then whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all like within this... when this receives, it's all parthita upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might describe different aspects differently, but the point of it is they're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, presence of feeling means presence of craving, for a Bhutujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can think of it, like, even in terms of, again, you can think of it even in terms of, um, just, like, when we spoke just a couple of hours ago,
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping yourself bound to a domain of sensuality makes you liable to whatever arises in that domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, keeping yourself bound to the domain of feelings makes yourself liable to whatever feelings arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you don't necessarily go after your feelings, the fact that you feel
[SPEAKER_00]: That feeling is appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes you liable to the other possibilities of that feeling that you're appropriating now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when that changes, you won't be able to escape it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that feeling changes, you won't be able to escape that change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you'll be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if feeling changes for even more pleasure, you won't be able to remain indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be pulled.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be hooked even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: If feeling changes to its pain, you'll be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that you're affected in the first place, that's what all... that's already what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the possibility... the fact that you won't be able to escape the possibility when it arises, that's dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have no control over possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense of control can only be exercised in regard to what's actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can start, like, thinking about probabilities and coefficients and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, just to give you a sense of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: In reality, possibility always remains a possibility, which means it can always be otherwise, which means your control is useless there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, you're so used to control, that you always see possibilities as secondary, as optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, fundamentally, structurally speaking, they come before the actual thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, possibilities, not being able to control them, yet depending upon them, that's what the nature of sankara is, exactly that very thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It determines everything, yet you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't determine it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, whatever you can determine, whatever you can determine, whatever you can intend, will be actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, there's always something possible in relation to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you can never, like, uproot it through your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can never take it up and really own it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the act of owning is already determined by the possibilities of ownership, which are not yours and cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding of feelings gets you out of the domain of
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you still feel, but your view or your relationship is completely changed to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then you can't really say that you feel anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just say feeling is there, but it's not... doesn't exist as my feeling, which is what existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to imagine how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be like in death, and then atom and separation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think my self would be cut.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you feel it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Self is cut.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when you look from the sense of... from the point of view of self, it feels like death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't even comprehend how can something be without existing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, as a practitioner you have to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practitioner has to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And back on to the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inseparable from the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't just examine craving as if an inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see the nature, you can distinguish, you can discern the nature, but it's simultaneously present with the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to discern the nature, to start discerning the particular difference between different types of craving, and I don't mean psychologically examining them, I just mean in pleasure,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to recognize the nature of craving in regard to the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, like, theoretically start pondering on what craving is, but to see it really in regard to the presently arisen pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same with pain, and same with neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem is, when there's a pleasant feeling, people would dismiss the entire thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Throw the baby out with the bathwater.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the degree of it is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What else there is what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you should stop doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through feeling, you can recognize the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: With feeling, craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why it's bhakti-bhakti, some part of description.
[SPEAKER_00]: While feeling craving to be even more accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, we say, when people start thinking, looking left and right...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see yourself forgetting, feeling, collision, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to, kind of, reverse-engineer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to recognize that you are... OK, I'm a kutujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, when I feel like, great, you don't see any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the first thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I feel, I crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, now the first reaction might be, oh, I must not feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is that you crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So how can you feel without craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you find that out, you're free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can feel,
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling arises irregardless of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not knowing that craving is redundant, you crave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but it's a pointless thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pointless endeavour.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, it's fair, also.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, it's just because, yeah, it... there is a thing is indifferent to the favour.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thing arises and ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you crave or not, makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your craving is just like trying to interfere, but again,
[SPEAKER_00]: All your craving can ever accomplish is, again, arising and ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is indifference to your craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why our craving can never be satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can never even be...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the idea, the conception of the idea of satisfaction is completely ignorant, because it just doesn't even pertain to the same domain, craving and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were generally mixed, it means craving could affect the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's really nothing to do with craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: To say, like, that feeling is indifferent, is... might even be to say too much, to make feelings... it sounds like feeling does care in a little way, it's indifferent, but it's... it's so... you know, like, to say something is ind... to... that is indifferent, is... is almost saying too much, giving it too much of concern, even.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so absolutely indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess, I guess, depending on how you start designating terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when I say different, I mean, I mean, like, equanimous.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, and that's what equanimity means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean I acknowledge you, but I don't care about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, like, you just... Not even... No, not... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to even acknowledge you, and that means, like, unshakable equanimity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize that aggregates cannot be acknowledged, nor can they acknowledge, because they're actively
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-enclosed, indifferent to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just the idea of them relating in any form can only arise from not knowing that they cannot relate in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you assume the relation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why upādāna takes out the aggregates through its own assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they remain indifferent to it, through and through, for the whole duration.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can never actually be accessed or affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So craving is like the unnecessary pressure of jumping around?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unnecessary pressure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unnecessary lean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unnecessary kind of inclination.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, in the same sense, you can measure your craving because you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can measure your
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering because of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously present, inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is pain present on account of something, it's not actually on account of that thing, but it's an account of the craving that's present, as it happens to be in regard to that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody says something that upsets you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not upset because what they said, what they've done, whatever, what they implied.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're upset because, in regard to that experience as a whole, you are craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since it's unpleasant, you're craving it to not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stop craving it to not be, the pain will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there and then, that very moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why often people get some relief through saying, oh, just be in the present moment, or just accept things, or just open up and don't resist, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can do that once, twice, a hundred times.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can do the whole life and you might have a more peaceful life.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not enough to bring understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, every religion teaches that, or very often, not every, maybe, but quite often, you hear that, through various gurujis or whatever else, so just be present, just don't resist, just accept, acceptance, and love, just love, like Christian love is a form of that kind of acceptance, you just love whatever comes your way and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, that is a rather, like, overriding, that's overshooting view.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you should not accept everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should accept only what you resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you don't resist, you shouldn't be accepting further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't apply the blanket acceptance, because there are different types of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, craving is subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you were to understand fully, correctly, with the right view, what craving is, then that would be the end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't have to do it, because now you understood it, and now it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the only reason you have to each time accept things, once they have arisen, is because there is no understanding in relation to their arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you still assume that they can be craved, therefore you crave, therefore you override it through acceptance, and you let it diminish, and then you feel better.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like a psychological cycle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma should take you to the point, and should be developed to such an extent, whereby you don't have to do anything in order to be free, or in order to not suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was always... that was always something that guided me, like, just... it always made sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had that, even as a layperson, when I started.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, if it's a true peace, it's something that you don't have to maintain.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's a true freedom from suffering, it's something that doesn't require me to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, I have to keep doing it until you reach it, but once it's fully developed, you don't have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything that was falling short of that cannot be the ultimate truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if...
[SPEAKER_00]: If they say in, like, psychology or whatever, well, when the pain arises or painful memory or something happens, well, you should do this and then you should do that and you should do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certainly, it helps in that linear psychological way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you have to do something in the first place, that's already a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, people don't see that, usually.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just take that for granted and then deal with the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is that you have to deal with the problem in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a big problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the biggest problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what dukkha, this is, is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not at ease because you know that there might be something you will need to do, you will have to do, in order to be at ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's making you uneasy.
[SPEAKER_00]: In maintenance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's exactly the point when it comes to craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to do this and then you gently soften or release.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just psychological babble that is revolving around the same view that it's failing to see that the fact that you have to do anything in the first place is already a big issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's THE issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of this is circumstantial afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, there is a degree of truth in like, oh, when there is a resistance, anger, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Accepting it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not resisting it will cancel out the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, you can do that for the right reasons and you can do that for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know what the deal with the craving and the feeling in there, if you have no concept of simultaneous dependence, that teaches samupādā, you'll never see... you'll never do it for the right reasons, which is why somebody can be quite evolved in that sense, but still be a putrījana.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's still doing the whole thing, rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's doing nibbāna for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So his sense of I am is still there, unaffected.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, painful feeling is painful, because you're resisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, okay, the first thing, I have to stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you stop resisting it,
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain might disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't get fooled by that and then, okay, see, I fixed it, that's the fix.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, each time the pain arises, I'll stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you develop this general view that overrides everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes corresponds to the nature of things, sometimes doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, if it doesn't even once, means it's not the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right view is always the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should not be fooled by when you... Yeah, you just stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just resign to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: This particular pain is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, how will I reach a point where it won't arise in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: And accepting... See, all of those psychological methods, techniques, where you just accept it, or you do this, or you do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that requires things to arise in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Between all that requires ignorance and craving in order to be able to deal with ignorance and craving, temporarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's not satisfactory for somebody who wants to be free.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it doesn't pertain to the nature of the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because Four Noble Truths are more than just, oh, you just accept or you just don't indulge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anybody can do that and see a degree of worldly benefit in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to have a direct, simultaneous insight into presence of craving, to the extent the craving is present, to that extent suffering is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only reason accepting, in regard to pain, works, is because it cancels out the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But accepting it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, I'm welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually already overdoing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you don't know, you go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as it happens, going that far also passes the craving and cancels it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you keep keep walking much further than you have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it happens that accepting also cancels out the craving in regard to the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to understand that the presence of craving means presence of suffering, and you just abandon craving, then you don't have to accept anything, nor refuse anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the attitude of accepting and refusing is aimed at the thing out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: The path that you cross, the distance that you cross in an act of accepting something that bothers you, happens to also walk past the degree of craving that is somewhere there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have no idea where that craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just go the whole distance and then the craving disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the feeling might have changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you might have been walking in a different direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have been thinking you're accepting the wrong thing and claiming you're applying to something different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you get it right, you get it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you don't know why you got it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you recognize it... And then again, again, because of that, people develop this general blanket view, so then they just accept everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: I love everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I pretend that people are not bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to see that actually, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's irrelevant whether you accept it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is relevant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you crave or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, what I was saying before is, there can be craving... sorry... accepting and craving... accepting or refusing implies craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there can be craving without accepting or refusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't accept or refuse, as a patujana, without craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still crave without accepting or refusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because craving is more primordial than act of accepting in regard to a particular thing or refusing the particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might do that initially, because your mind is not subtle enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is to take you to the point whereby you recognize that the craving is a problem, and that's where the solution is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, abandoning craving, then, will prevent the problem from arising in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the act of accepting or refusing will not be the act of accepting or refusing through craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will just be agreeable, disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, by knowing where the real problem of craving is, you won't have to pretend
[SPEAKER_00]: And try to cover everything up and paint in your blanket view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's a good person.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: He means well.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He acts like a foolish idiot and it's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not upset on account of it, even if he's insulting you, because you don't crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, a recognition of someone's idiocy and stupidity aimed at you, that is offending you, that offense won't cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can recognize this is disagreeable, but you won't suffer on that account because you won't crave in regard to what is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... and you still don't have to accept what he's saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you accept it when you know it's lots of nonsense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you have to pretend that he's good?
[SPEAKER_00]: So people do that because they don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same way we spoke about the subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not recognizing the subha-nimitta and asubha-nimitta, and dealing it at the level of significance, people need to... they overshoot the mark, and they look at the decomposed bodies and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That helps initially, in the same sense, accepting could help initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: But only so that you can be able to recognize that, actually, the problem is way beyond this.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is that I'm moved in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't want to have to go around and look at the pictures of decomposed bodies whenever I have lust arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's way too much lust, when I got careless, then it can help snap you back.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind needs to be established in regard to beautiful or ugly as something that is ugly, as something that is unwanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where dispassion is reached.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can have all the beauty in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind sees it as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you each time keep running back to the pictures in the super, you have a nice little collection, and it will work less and less.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's exactly this accepting attitude, like, oh, just be present and accept whatever comes your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can come as a revelation to somebody who's never present and never accepted anything that comes his way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, through accepting it, he does actually, accidentally as well, doesn't crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's only initially, because he just took the whole bulk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sooner or later, that will wear out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it will stop having that effect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, you start craving in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving doesn't stay always in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, as a subha always shoots the mark, if done improperly, accepting or refusing, or I refuse pleasure, would mean you deny all the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think the pleasant feeling is the problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: You deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think the painful feeling is the problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: You accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But neither painful nor pleasant feeling, nor neutral, are actually the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have no craving in regard to what you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the bad feeling arises on account of what somebody said, you can see it clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, what he said is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was actually wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this disagreeable feeling is the result of something wrong I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like sometimes when arahants are reprimanded by the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, because there won't be any craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't take it personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your behavior will just be modified, according to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, this is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if they just criticize you, and there is a disagreeable feeling on account of the words you're hearing, and you realize they have no idea what they talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're deluded, ignorant, angry person.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, thank you, brother.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're weird.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't want to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you either dismiss them or leave yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to deal with an idiot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's being praised.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you won't crave being praised.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be taken by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes praise is a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can confirm it, as the Buddha did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I am the greatest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes they praise you for completely wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't be intoxicated by either of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I look back now, there's no intense, like, intense feelings or...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't notice any intense... No, no, it's a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the hardest one to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greatly in regards to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as we spoke before, clearly there are indolence, like resting, feeling secure, feeling safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling calm, feeling peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless it's the peace of an arahant, then it's not the peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should not relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can lay down and sleep, but infernally, your mind should never relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't need to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body needs to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body needs to sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm really tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to sit down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You sit down, but with your body sitting down, your mind sits down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is an excuse for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha meant when he said the consciousness should not rest and get established upon anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a cow, if it leans onto the wall, it's eaten by the insects, if it lays on the ground, if it leans on the tree, if it... it's eaten by whatever it leans on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that doesn't require effort, either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require you like... you know, clenching your teeth, you know, like enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just an attitude of mind in regard to laying in your bed all day.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just having that mindfulness still.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That attitude requires mindfulness, which is why mindfulness is always needed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have too much of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mindfulness, to the extent necessary... And persistence, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Persistence is the biggest... Energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, persistence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental drilling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making that mental effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't tire you bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, yeah, if...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like, you know, get up, keep walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just go to sleep again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people give in to sleep as a form of... mind goes to sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: If... if you go to sleep only when your body really needs to sleep, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you go to sleep as a psychological result of, you know, you don't want to deal with stuff or... the mind is resting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I like to come back from work, open a can of beer and, you know, watch my favorite TV program.
[SPEAKER_00]: I deserve it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've been working eight hours a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's obviously the crudest example.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can, you know, live in a kutti without a TV, without anything, and, yeah, I've been meditating for 10 hours, and now I'm gonna go and sit down and have a cup of tea and rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, do that, but that's still not an excuse for your mind to sit down and rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: No is an excuse that when you are busy, for your mind to go and get busy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think to see the distinction, this is my body and it will do what it has to do, what it needs to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I walk, I think... And keep your mind alert in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what mindfulness of the body means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean you're like a robot touching.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means basically you're mindful and aware of whatever your body is doing throughout the day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actions, intentions and stuff, you're mindful in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't lay in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't come into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't become it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I would say, like, a good... a good night or a good day, so... you... you contemplate and contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you're laying down... Yeah, you... you can give up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop contemplating now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've been working all day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it will continue, kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether if it continues or not, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the only thing you should be concerned when you're, okay, I've been making effort all day, I can't do it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go and have a break.
[SPEAKER_00]: Physically and mentally, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't allow your mind to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, always keep an eye on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that doesn't require... that requires zero effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the I, the awareness, the degree of awareness, is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you'd be dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you... that's why mindfulness comes with understanding of what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The awareness is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean, oh, the awareness is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The degree of awareness is always there for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how aggregates work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it just means that whatever is arising, there is a degree of awareness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, that thing will not be manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop doing the awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just recognize it as coming, being implied in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind never forgets that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that way, you never lose mindfulness, even in the act of forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: You forget something particularly, but you don't forget the nature of forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that resting, that welcoming, is delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what delighting is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't delight, it doesn't welcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've been sleeping all day, and wake up, and you still feel like crap, and you can't get up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just physically wiped.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you go back to sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine, as long as you don't welcome it, internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome anything internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean you have to stop doing it externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a distinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't welcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And through that non-welcoming, if it was genuinely bodily tiredness, yeah, you'll sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it ain't, it will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm not actually sleeping anymore, which means it wasn't bothering, it was something my mind wanted to do, because there was no other distractions to keep me up, engaged, so I just couldn't deal with boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, when you're bored, fine, we're bored, don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can keep not doing anything, but never welcome it for a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can keep doing, but, oh, I want to lay down, I want to go for a nice pleasant walk, climb the waterfalls.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it at the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it for any time in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind always remains alert in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require any effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beginning, obviously, you feel like, you know, spoiling the party.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just because you're overshooting the mark, initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're all uptight.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not want this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, don't welcome that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the craving for being and non-being is just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the feeling, eh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for being, craving for non-being and for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, craving for sensuality is craving for being or non-being through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's even more proliferate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving for a thing, for something to be... For a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving for a particular this or a particular that, means central craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you can stop craving in regard to a particular object, particular objects of your senses, and then you abandon the central craving, but then you still have the more subtle craving for being and the absence of being, non-being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving for a phenomenon to be or a phenomenon to disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still a subtle kind of affinity and resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, much subtler than actually fully developed craving for sensual objects or absence of them, if they are unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why anāgāmī is not free from those two types of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't love and hate, which pertains to the infatuation or revulsion in regard to central objects, but you can still experience craving in regard to phenomena and absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean craving for the old hidden lights in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhādeva was affected by that woman laughing at him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't hate her, because he was affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He craved the non-being of that experience, which is what snapped him out and made him realize.
[SPEAKER_00]: And say, like when anāgāmīs don't, lay anāgāmīs, when they don't become bhikkhus or bhikkhunis and go forth, is when they still
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they crave for the notion of the sense of duty in regard to their family.
[SPEAKER_00]: They... No, that's the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they stay to look after their parents.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why they don't become Arhats.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they abandon sensuality, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't see your craving directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, there, so now I'll stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, what you have to watch in the back of your mind is whether you delight in delight in an acceptance or delight in aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anger offers a form of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says something, and you feel angry, and then you delight in telling them off, or revenging, payback, or ranting about them to somebody else, which gives you full relief, like, yeah, yeah, it's like this, it's like that, it's like that, it's like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're delighting in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to not crave,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can know for sure, if there is a suffering present, craving is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you indirectly, directly do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you know what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an indirect action, but if it's fully known how it can be done, it can be done directly, in its indirect nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, well, watching the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you watch the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm welcoming it, therefore I will not welcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through not welcoming, you cannot crave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through not craving, the suffering won't be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you also need to recognize that, because the degree of displeasure will still be there, but that's not what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the understanding is the, like, the core of the whole thing, and the reason for liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody can do this, but without understanding,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without being able to discern what he's told to discern, I discern the pain, arisen on its own, from the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you discern that, it is the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like two sheets of glass, identical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you know that there are two, you won't know that there are two.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no difference between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: Except that there are two.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Too much suffering and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Physical pain, it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, see, that when you say physical pain, people usually associate bodily sensation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's not physical pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Annoyance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hearing somebody shouting abuse at you is a physical pain, because it came through your physical ears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing a disgusting image is a physical pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's pain that is in regard to what
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, having a lynch chopped off is also physical pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, mental pain is in regard to any of that type of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your mind is affected by it as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is in general pain, if you're unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there is the feeling of, am I bothered on account of feeling unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I feel an urge to deal with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, oh, I'm craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is craving present, and that's the reason why I suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the problem, not the unpleasant feeling that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it says, like, he develops three, four knowledge, and
[SPEAKER_00]: becomes an arahant, and he recognizes, any disturbance that is left for me now, will be disturbance on account of this five senses, on account of this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's often said, ah, just endure unpleasant, unpleasant words and abuse, or whatever, done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just endure it, Brahman, you're, you're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said that to Angulimala.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would Buddha need to say that to Angulimala, when he was already an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you would think, wouldn't you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're just reminding him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is... there will be still this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of it can ever, even remotely, conceive the pain, like suffering, which is what pain is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disagreeable feeling is not pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not wanting disagreeable feeling, that's what pain is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you could overshoot, as you say, by feeling a cramp in your leg or knee, starting to twist or
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already misplacing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're thinking it's out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to endure?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you should do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: You should move and then recognize the pain or the guilt that arises on account that you couldn't hold up your determination to not move.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where suffering is more likely to be found than enduring in your twisted joint and then turning yourself into an invalid because you're such a keen meditator.
[SPEAKER_00]: The anxiety, that hollow feeling that arises on the fact that you could not hold up a determination that has a reason, I will not move.
[SPEAKER_00]: I moved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, what does that show you?
[SPEAKER_00]: You were not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let that arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't bother torturing your body and twisting your knees and, you know, pushing the nails through your skin or whatever else they do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, let the guilt, let the anxiety, let those painful mental feelings arise, because they all have in common suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no doubt about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can suffer in regard to the bodily, what you heard, what you did.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to this type of suffering, that is always suffering, which is why those things cannot arise in another hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disagreeable feeling can arise on account of somebody shouting abuse at him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreeable feeling might arise on account of somebody praising him.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of those things will induce lust or aversion anymore, ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certainly, you'll never ever experience anxiety, guilt, doubt, and all those mental painful feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is that difference between mental and bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it just means, on what account has it arisen?
[SPEAKER_00]: But every feeling is a mental feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't feel feelings in your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I feel something in my back.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You perceive something in your back.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel it in regard to your whole body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a particular aspect of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm about to lose my hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel very scared now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And very, very afraid.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what hurts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the perception of whatever's happening in your hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't feel any physical pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the body is, you know, rational.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to keep moving here and there, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's annoying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I try not to scratch, I just try to
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might initially not want to scratch, just because, oh, you're not sure where to look for the craving, or where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is not the need.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is not the arising of the itch and the scratch.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is whether you imply craving through doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether action constantly implies craving, in which case it's an action, it's a karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove craving formation, then karma ceases to be karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it's just a response to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Significance, intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be careful in doing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should put up with things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything you become stronger,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you haven't... that doesn't mean that you've gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the survey, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else comes along.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's why, like in the sutta, some monks, you know, needed ascetic practices, because that would be making them genuinely look at the right direction, in the right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some actually was completely counterproductive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through ascetic practices, for them, they were overshooting the mark, and they could not see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why applying the blanket of, we should all be doing this, we should all be doing that, is ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to have to wait for something big to happen, or do something really dramatic to see how it happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose, naturally, things will happen that are quite dramatic, so to speak, or quite intense, or you lose a limb, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even if that doesn't happen, the fact that it can happen, if you dwell on it, that will become dramatic in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how people lose their minds.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't lose their minds when painful things happen to them directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They lose their minds when they start, gradually, like they get eroded by the recognition of the possibility that they're completely exposed, at any given time, at any given second, to absolutely anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It freaks you out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when something bad happens, it's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's painful, whatever, but it happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when there's something...
[SPEAKER_01]: Anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what it's meant in the sutta as being praying to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't actually suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you don't have to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you recognize that you are praying
[SPEAKER_00]: To suffering, like, descending upon you, so to speak, for whatever reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: You...
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine, how would you feel if you were a prey?
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't a problem in front of you, but you just feel like, at any time, something can pounce on you and hunt you down and get you like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if nothing does, the fact that this... that's what brings you... makes you mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: The anticipation in the war, like, when people are in war,
[SPEAKER_00]: Anticipate... that's when, you know, they go gray and lose their, lose their, you know, age 50 years overnight, because of their weight of, oh, I might die.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's much easier when the fight breaks, start, oh, it's right there in front, so you just fight or not, but it's the anticipation of the fight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, it's the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anticipation of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels he's prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the fact that you'll suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's also painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you can suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can suffer again and again and again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine if there is...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are a prey to something.
[SPEAKER_00]: If something is hunting you constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to contemplate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you might try to bring it up in particular things, and you might bring it up to an extent in regard to particular things, but you kind of leave yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that sort of incomplete contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start thinking about the fact that you'll die, stop breathing, drown, it's risky, because it can really freak you out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, it does hammer it back on.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you so are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you are liable to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you fear death,
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, ah, there is a fear in regard to something like which means there is something you're still holding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to that degree, you're liable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it gives you the... Well, it kind of... ...the motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motivation, it sort of, like, delineates, delineates, that's the word, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Delineates, outlines the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reminds you of where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you shouldn't cut lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, you know, that's what dhamma is, that's what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you deal with that problem, you overcome death, fear of death, of anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: No particular problem arising on account of a particular instance, you know, can ever bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just gonna be disagreeable, agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimately, you left it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, if you're imagining linearly, in a process, then it's not really akālika.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it can always be akālika, in the sense that any linear process is present as such, as an adjacent thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mindful of that means, ah, right there, right now, so that is akālika.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter what stage of your linear contemplation of death, you recognize, I will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not doing the contemplation so to actually die, but doing contemplation to allow that fear of death to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see on what level it arises and then realize this is what needs to be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even that fear, if it's unpleasant, it's not unpleasant because of the dying and because of the fear, it's unpleasant because you crave and you so don't want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you remove that not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't welcome the unwanting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you won't be afraid of death either.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only thing you'll be, is very mindful, if the death comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even just the thought of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or just the thought of death will immediately bring the mindfulness, because that's where mindfulness comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, like Sotāpanna has been negligent throughout life, the moment of death, he will realize the fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where the fruit is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm trying again to...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, because I know...
[SPEAKER_01]: I do know that there's a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: I leave the situation, I get caught up in another situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I go out of the city or whatever, then I get caught up in a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can still get caught up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I pick up a phone, I can fill a pool or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes I don't see the craving
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's why you have to have that wisdom to recognize, oh, the problem is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether I'm now using this environment to avoid the recognition and reminders that the problem is still there, or whether I'm using it to really practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's like how you eat your food and why you eat your food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you allow it to become because it's essential, or whether you keep in mind the real reasons.